A Finding Aid to the Bob Thompson Papers, 1949-2005, in the Archives of American Art AAA.thombob
Archives of American Art
Bob Thompson papers
1949-2005
AAA.thombob
Archives of American Art
1.8 Linear feet
The papers of figurative painter Bob Thompson measure 1.8 linear feet and date from 1949 to 2005. Thompson’s career is documented through scattered biographical material, including two videocassettes; business correspondence between his wife Carol Thompson and various galleries, dealers, businesses, and friends; creative and editorial writings by Thompson as well as commemorative tributes and notes written by others; business records of the appraisal, sale, study, and exhibition of Thompson’s work after his death; exhibition catalogs and publicity, news clippings, and other printed material; and photographs of the artist, exhibitions, and art.
Thompson, Bob, 1937-1966
Scope and Contents note
The papers of figurative painter Bob Thompson measure 1.8 linear feet and date from 1949 to 2005. Thompson’s career is documented through scattered biographical material, including two videocassettes; business correspondence between his wife Carol Thompson and various galleries, dealers, businesses, and friends; creative and editorial writings by Thompson as well as commemorative tributes and notes written by others; business records of the appraisal, sale, study, and exhibition of Thompson’s work after his death; exhibition catalogs and publicity, news clippings, and other printed material; and photographs of the artist, exhibitions, and art.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Elaine Plenda, the artist's sister-in-law, in 2006, 2010, 2011, and 2012. The papers were initially organized by Carol Thompson, Bob Thompson's wife.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of video recording requires advance notice. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
Bob Thompson (1937-1966) was a figurative painter in New York City.
Thompson was born in Louisville, Kentucky, and studied art at the University of Louisville before moving to New York City in 1958. In 1960, he married Carol Plenda and the couple lived in Paris, France (1961-1962) and Ibiza, Spain (1962-1963), returned to New York City (1963-1965), and then settled in Rome, Italy (1965-1966) before Thompson’s tragic death at the age of 28 from a drug overdose.
Thompson was known for his reworkings of traditional compositions borrowed from canonical masters, including Piero della Francesca, Masaccio, and Goya, which he integrated into more elemental works with unnatural color, silhouetted forms, and suggested space. Influenced by jazz, Thompson’s art rebutted contemporary abstract form but retained its sense of freedom, rhythm, and expression.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as six series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1953-2003 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1971-2000 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Writings, 1949-1998 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1973-2001 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1960-2005 (Boxes 1-3, OV 4; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, 1951-2000 (Boxes 2-3; 0.4 linear feet)
Thompson, Carol; African American artists; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs
- Biographical Material, 1953-2003; Series 1; 5 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains scattered biographical material, including two copies of "Bob Thompson Happening," a film by Dorothy Levitt Beskind from 1965 and copied to videocassette (VHS) for a 1999 exhibition at the Whitney Museum, with footage of Thompson in New York and Provincetown, Massachusetts, and an appearance by Hans Hofmann; timelines of his personal and professional life and exhibitions through 2003; miscellaneous biographical material, including a driver’s safety certificate, high school graduation program, letter of admission to Boston University, funeral program, and obituary; and a typewritten transcript of the “Bob Thompson: His Life and Friendships” panel featuring Bill Barrell, Emilio Cruz, Mimi Gross, Edward Levine, Jay Milder, Sheila Milder, and Anne Tabachnick.
  - "Bob Thompson Happening" (1965) by Dorothy Levitt Beskind, Exhibition Copy for Whitney Museum, 1999; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) duplicate video copies made from original 16mm film; film not with collection (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Life/Exhibition Timeline, circa 2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, 1953-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Transcript of “Bob Thompson: His Life and Friendships", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1971-2000; Series 2; 3 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence is between the artist’s wife Carol Thompson and various galleries, dealers, businesses, and friends and concerns mostly business matters with some personal letters interspersed as well. This series consists of letters exchanged with Judith Wilson, an African American art historian who studied Thompson, as well as general correspondence, which includes letters from business entities as well as from Bessie Thompson, the artist’s mother.
  - Correspondence with Judith Wilson, 1983-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1971-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- Writings, 1949-1998; Series 3; 2 Folders Box 1
  Writings by the artist include church speeches Thompson gave as a teenager; a letter to the editor of the National Hot Rod Association; a poem “Today Was My Everyone Day” handwritten on the verso of an announcement card for The Jazz Gallery; and an artist statement from 1965. Writings by others include notes from Thompson’s mother Bessie; fourteen tributes to the artist in poem and anecdote form by Margaret Bridwell, Dario Covi, Carl Crodel, Allen Ginsberg, LeRoi Jones, Mary H. Martin, Mary Spencer May, Meyer Schapiro, and A.B. Spellman; as well as other writings by friends and wife Carol Thompson.
  - Writings by Bob Thompson, 1949-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writings by Others, 1955-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Personal Business Records, 1973-2001; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Personal business records document the appraisal, sale, study, and exhibition of Thompson’s work after his death. Documents take the form of sales and price lists, exhibition checklists, invoices, loan agreements, and correspondence.
  - California Afro-American Museum, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Christie's, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Daniel Goldreyer, Ltd., 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - David Anderson Gallery, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Donald Morris Gallery, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Inventories and Price Lists, circa 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Martha Jackson Gallery, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Business Records, 1978-1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pacifico Fine Art Gallery, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Reading & O'Reilly, Inc., 1991-1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Robert Miller Galleries, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Skoto Gallery, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1976-1992 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Studio Museum in Harlem, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Vanderwoude Tananbaum Gallery, 1981-1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1986-2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1995-2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Printed Material, 1960-2005; Series 5; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, OV 4
  Printed material includes publicity for exhibitions; exhibition catalogs; magazines and sales catalogs; news clippings concerning Thompson, his art, exhibitions, and death; unmarked postcards of artwork; posters for exhibitions; and press releases for exhibitions and the artist’s passing.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Brochures, 1964-2001 (Box 1, Folder 29-31)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1964-2001 (Box 1, Folder 32-36)
  - Magazines and Sales Catalogs, 1987-2000 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - News Clippings, 1961-2005 (Box 1, Folder 38-43)
  - News Clippings, 1983-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Postcards, 1974-1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Posters and Signage, 1960-2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Oversized material housed in Box 3, Folder 2 and OV 4.
  - Press Releases, 1966-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Exhibition Signage from Box 2, Folder 3, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Posters from Box 2, Folder 3, circa 1960-1964 (Box OV 4)
- Photographs, 1951-2000; Series 6; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  This series includes personal photographs of the artist alone as well as with friends and family in Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania; Provincetown, Massachusetts; Paris, France; Rome and Florence, Italy; Ibiza, Spain; and New York City, specifically at the Rivington Street studio, Billard Palace on 14th Street, and Slugs Jazz Club.
  Photographs of friends and family include images of Irene and Bill Barrell, Robert Beauchamp, Ornette Coleman, Robert Frank, Lorenzo Hale, Christopher Lane, Malachy McCourt, Sheila and Jay Milder, Moondog, Steve Pepper, Dorothea Rockburne, and A.B. Spellman, as well as the artist’s mother Bessie Thompson and wife Carol Thompson. Also found here are an album of photographs taken by Charles Rotmil showing the Thompsons’ wedding reception at the Clinton Street loft on December 16, 1960; albums of exhibition installations, opening receptions, and personal photographs; slides of the Detroit Institute of Arts exhibition; and loose photographs of artwork, singly and in exhibitions.
  - Photographs of Bob Thompson, 1951-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Oversized photographs housed in Box 3, Folder 1.
  - Photographs of Friends and Family, 1951-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Album, Wedding Reception, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Album, Exhibitions, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Album, Vanderwoude Tananbaum Exhibition, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Slides of Detroit Institute of Arts Exhibition, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of J.B. Speed Exhibition, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Exhibitions, 1978-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Studio Museum Exhibition, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Thompson, circa 1965-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Others, circa 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Oversized Photographs from Box 2, Folders 5-6 and 15-16, 1951-1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes photographs of the artist, alone and with his mother, and photographs of artwork.
  - Oversized Album, Personal Photographs, 1960-1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)